# **Austin P. Spencer**

Northwestern University Department of Chemistry Evanston, IL 60208 austin.spencer@northwestern.edu (336) 302 7712 Google Scholar Profile: goo.gl/KXHsAU

LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/austinpspencer

Physical chemist with more than a decade of research experience in ultrafast spectroscopy and materials characterization. Investigated photophysics in chemical systems ranging from nanomaterials and proteins to organic polymers and small molecules.

- Experienced *team project manager* with proven mentoring and leadership skills.
- Strong record of *effective communication* through research presentations and scientific writing, with *16 peer-reviewed publications* (and counting).
- Adaptable to varying projects, mastering new skills as needed to complete an assignment.
- Extensive experience in *instrument design and development*, including optics, software, and electronics.

### **Education**

Ph.D., Chemistry

August 2014

University of Colorado Boulder

**B.S., Chemistry** with Honors and Distinction; minor in Computer Science
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

May 2009

## Experience

#### **Postdoctoral Researcher**

February 2018-present

Northwestern University, Department of Chemistry; Advisor: Lin X. Chen

- Led graduate students in the development and execution of collaborative research projects.
- Spearheaded a new project to study energy transfer in solar energy harvesting materials.
- Designed and built a time-resolved spectroscopy instrument and trained students in its use.

#### **Postdoctoral Researcher**

August 2014-February 2018

Northwestern University, Department of Chemistry; Advisor: Elad Harel

- Advised graduate and undergraduate students on project development and publication of results, and trained them on experimental techniques.
- Designed and built highly-cited time-resolved spectroscopies, including 4D electronic-Raman spectroscopy, single-shot 2D spectroscopy, and compressive sensing detection.
- Probed electronic-vibrational coupling in CdSe quantum dots and photosynthetic proteins, demonstrating the strong interactions between excitons and phonons.

#### Research Assistant

August 2009-August 2014

University of Colorado Boulder, Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry; Advisor: David M. Jonas

- Studied charge carrier dynamics in colloidal InAs and PbS quantum dots, exposing interactions between excitons within the same nanoparticle.
- Developed computational simulations for the modeling of multidimensional spectra.

### **Undergraduate Researcher**

December 2007-May 2009

University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Department of Chemistry; Advisor: Tomas Baer Eötvös Loránd University (Budapest, Hungary); Advisor: Bálint Sztáray

• Investigated UV photodissociation and thermochemistry of halo-alkanes and halo-silanes.

## Technical skills

- **Spectroscopy** two-dimensional electronic transient absorption UV-Vis photoelectron
- **Optics and Lasers** ultrafast optics interferometry laser pulse characterization (spatial, temporal, and spectral) pulse shaping
- **Materials** semiconductor nanomaterials (quantum dots) organic photovoltaic polymers and small molecules photosynthetic protein complexes
- **Experiment/instrument development** robust optical design high-speed data acquisition technique characterization, calibration, and documentation
- **Software development** instrument control and real-time synchronization data acquisition modular, object-oriented design
- Analytical methods mass spectrometry NMR chromatography (HPLC, GC)
- **Data analysis and modeling** signal and image processing global analysis methods linear and nonlinear optimization
- **Programming** MATLAB LabVIEW C Linux/Bash Python Mathematica Fortran Java
- Electronic engineering analog digital microcontrollers PCB design test & measurement

## **Awards and Recognitions**

Cover & Feature article in The Journal of Physical Chemistry C<sup>4</sup>

November 2018

"Four-Dimensional Coherent Spectroscopy of Complex Molecular Systems in Solution"

### Featured in *Science*: 4D electronic-Raman spectroscopy<sup>9</sup>

**June 2017** 

J. Goodknight, A. Aspuru-Guzik. Taking six-dimensional spectra in finite time. *Science* **2017**, *356*, 1333–1333; DOI: 10.1126/science.aan2842

#### Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship

Summer 2008

University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

**Eagle Scout** 

#### **Publications**

- 1. M. S. Kirschner, Y. Jeong, A. P. Spencer, N. E. Watkins, X.-M. Lin, G. C. Schatz, L. X. Chen, R. D. Schaller. Phonon-induced plasmon-exciton coupling changes probed via oscillation-associated spectra. *Appl. Phys. Lett.* **2019**, *115*, 111903; DOI: 10.1063/1.5116836
- 2. P. E. Ohno, H. Chang, A. P. Spencer, Y. Liu, M. D. Boamah, H.-f. Wang, F. M. Geiger. Beyond the Gouy–Chapman Model with Heterodyne-Detected Second Harmonic Generation. *J. Phys. Chem. Lett.* **2019**, *10*, 2328–2334; DOI: 10.1021/acs.jpclett.9b00727
- 3. A. P. Spencer, W. K. Peters, N. R. Neale, D. M. Jonas. Carrier Dynamics and Interactions for Bulk-Like Photoexcitation of Colloidal Indium Arsenide Quantum Dots. *J. Phys. Chem. C* **2018**; DOI: 10.1021/acs.jpcc.8b09671

- 4. A. P. Spencer, W. O. Hutson, E. Harel. Four-Dimensional Coherent Spectroscopy of Complex Molecular Systems in Solution. *J. Phys. Chem. C* **2018**; DOI: 10.1021/acs.jpcc.8b09184
- 5. S. Irgen-Gioro, A. P. Spencer, W. O. Hutson, E. Harel. Coherences of Bacteriochlorophyll a Uncovered Using 3D-Electronic Spectroscopy. *J. Phys. Chem. Lett.* **2018**, *9*, 6077–6081; DOI: 10.1021/acs.jpclett.8b02217
- 6. A. P. Spencer, W. O. Hutson, S. Irgen-Gioro, E. Harel. Exciton-Phonon Spectroscopy of Quantum Dots Below the Single-Particle Homogeneous Line Width. *J. Phys. Chem. Lett.* **2018**, 1503–1508; DOI: 10.1021/acs.jpclett.8b00065
- 7. W. O. Hutson, A. P. Spencer, E. Harel. Ultrafast Four-Dimensional Coherent Spectroscopy by Projection Reconstruction. *J. Phys. Chem. Lett.* **2018**, 1034–1040; DOI: 10.1021/acs.jpclett.8b00122
- 8. <u>A. P. Spencer</u>, R. J. Hill, W. K. Peters, D. Baranov, B. Cho, A. Huerta-Viga, A. R. Carollo, A. C. Curtis, D. M. Jonas. Sample exchange by beam scanning with applications to noncollinear pump-probe spectroscopy at kilohertz repetition rates. *Rev. Sci. Instrum.* **2017**, *88*, 064101; DOI: 10.1063/1.4986628
- 9. A. P. Spencer, W. O. Hutson, E. Harel. Quantum coherence selective 2D Raman–2D electronic spectroscopy. *Nat. Commun.* **2017**, *8*, 14732; DOI: 10.1038/ncomms14732
- 10. W. O. Hutson, A. P. Spencer, E. Harel. Isolated Ground-State Vibrational Coherence Measured by Fifth-Order Single-Shot Two-Dimensional Electronic Spectroscopy. *J. Phys. Chem. Lett.* **2016**, 3636–3640; DOI: 10.1021/acs.jpclett.6b01733
- 11. A. P. Spencer, B. Spokoyny, S. Ray, F. Sarvari, E. Harel. Mapping multidimensional electronic structure and ultrafast dynamics with single-element detection and compressive sensing. *Nat. Commun.* **2016**, *7*, 10434; DOI: 10.1038/ncomms10434
- 12. A. P. Spencer, B. Spokoyny, E. Harel. Enhanced-Resolution Single-Shot 2DFT Spectroscopy by Spatial Spectral Interferometry. *J. Phys. Chem. Lett.* **2015**, 945–950; DOI: 10.1021/acs.jpclett.5b00273
- 13. A. P. Spencer, H. Li, S. T. Cundiff, D. M. Jonas. Pulse Propagation Effects in Optical 2D Fourier-Transform Spectroscopy: Theory. *J. Phys. Chem. A* **2015**, *119*, 3936–3960; DOI: 10.1021/acs.jpca.5b00001
- 14. B. Cho, V. Tiwari, R. J. Hill, W. K. Peters, T. L. Courtney, A. P. Spencer, D. M. Jonas. Absolute Measurement of Femtosecond Pump–Probe Signal Strength. *J. Phys. Chem. A* **2013**, *117*, 6332–6345; DOI: 10.1021/jp4019662
- 15. H. Li, A. P. Spencer, A. Kortyna, G. Moody, D. M. Jonas, S. T. Cundiff. Pulse Propagation Effects in Optical 2D Fourier-Transform Spectroscopy: Experiment. *J. Phys. Chem. A* **2013**, *117*, 6279–6287; DOI: 10.1021/jp4007872
- 16. N. S. Shuman, A. P. Spencer, T. Baer. Experimental Thermochemistry of SiCl3R (R = Cl, H, CH3, C2H5, C2H3, CH2Cl, SiCl3), SiCl3+, and SiCl3•. *J. Phys. Chem. A* **2009**, *113*, 9458–9466; DOI: 10.1021/jp9054186
- 17. A. P. Spencer, *TPEPICO Spectroscopy of SiCl4, SiCl3CH3, SiCl3CH2Cl, SiCl3C2H3, and SiCl3C2H5: Thermochemistry of Trichlorosilane Derivatives, Honors Thesis, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill, NC,* **2009**. URL